Guide to the Tamiment Library Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Collection TAM.507
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.), 2007-present
  - Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association (MEBA), Dec 2009-present
    The Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association (MEBA) is the oldest maritime trade union in the United States still currently in existence, established in 1875. MEBA primarily represents licensed mariners, especially deck and engine officers working in the United States Merchant Marine aboard U.S.-flagged vessels. It is a member union of the AFL–CIO. MEBA officers work in both the oceans and the Great Lakes in many settings, including on container ships, tankers (including LNG carriers), cruise ships, drillships, tugboats, ferries, and fireboats, as well as in various capacities in the shore side ship transport and marine industries and on government-contracted ships of the United States Maritime Administration's Ready Reserve Force and United States Navy's Military Sealift Command.
  - Metro New York Labor Communications Council, May 2010-present
    The Metro New York Labor Communications Council (Metro), established in 1974, is a council which consists of editors, writers, artists, photographers, graphic designers, web designers, radio program producers, labor public relations specialists, and video producers from public and private sector trade unions, related organizations, and others in the labor movement. Metro provides a forum to exchange ideas and information and to discuss the problems and questions that confront labor communicators in their work. The Council offers skills orientated workshops, seminars, journalism awards, and an annual convention to discuss relevant issues regarding the labor movement. Metro is affiliated with the International Labor Communications Association of the AFL-CIO, and cooperates with the New York City Central Labor Council.
  - Million Worker March Movement, Jul 2011-Feb 2013
    The Million Worker March was a rally on October 17, 2004 on in Washington DC. The rally was against perceived attacks on the working class families. Approximately 10000 people marched on Washington.
  - National Air Traffic Controllers Association (NATCA), Dec 2009-present
    National Air Traffic Controllers Association (NATCA) represents over 20,000 controllers, engineers and other safety-related professionals, including engineers, traffic management coordinators and staff specialists, with membership from every state, territory and possession of the United States. Certified in 1987, NATCA is affiliated with the AFL-CIO.
  - National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians, Communication Workers of America, Mar 2009-present
    National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians-Communications Workers of America (NABET-CWA), founded in 1934, is a Union of workers who are employed in the broadcasting, distributing, telecasting, recording, cable, video, sound recording and related industries in North America. NABET-CWA has contracts with ABC, NBC, FOX and other networks, as well as local TV stations across the country and members include engineers, photographers, editors, directors, technicians, graphic artists, traffic coordinators, clerical workers, truck operators, writers, reporters, anchors, producers and others in the television and cable industry.
  - National Association of Letter Carriers (NALC), Dec 2009-present
    The National Association of Letter Carriers (NALC) is an American labor union, representing non-rural letter carriers employed by the United States Postal Service. It was founded in 1889.
  - National Domestic Workers Alliance, Oct 2011-present
    Founded in 2007, the National Domestic Workers Alliance organizes domestic workers in the United States to improve their living and working conditions, win respect and justice from employers and government for exploited domestic workers; challenge racism and sexism; end the exclusion of domestic workers from recognition and protection; and build a movement of migrant workers to fight the labor displacement and exploitation created by globalization.
  - National Education Association, Dec 2009-present
    The National Education Association (NEA), founded in 1857, is the largest professional organization and largest labor union in the United States, representing public school teachers and other support personnel, faculty and staffers at colleges and universities, retired educators, and college students preparing to become teachers. The NEA has 3.2 million members and is headquartered in Washington, D.C. It has affiliate organizations in every state and in more than 14,000 communities across the United States.
  - National Guestworker Alliance, May 2012-present
    National Guestworker Alliance, founded in 2005 as the Alliance of Guestworkers, is a membership organization of guestworkers and organizes members in labor camps across the United States to win collective dignity at work. They also work to gain fairness in the terms of migration and partner with local workers to strengthen U.S. social movements for racial and economic justice. The website contains information on guestworker rights, news, and current programs.
  - National Labor College, May 2012-present
    National Labor College (NLC), located in Silver Spring, MD, is the only accredited higher education institution in the United States devoted exclusively to educating union members, leaders, and staff. It was established as a training center by the AFL-CIO in 1969 to strengthen union member education and organizing skills. The website contains information on admissions, academic programs, alumni, blogs, conference services and their online campus.
  - National Mobilization Against Sweatshops, Sep 2007-present
    The National Mobilization Against Sweatshops is a grassroots educational campaign dedicated to ending sweatshop conditions for all working people. It was founded in New York City in 1996. The site includes transcripts of several oral histories of sweatshop workers.
  - National Nurses United, Jan 2009-present
    National Nurses United, with more than 150,000 members from across the country, is the largest union and professional association of registered nurses in America. Founded in December 2009, NNU brought together the California Nurses Association/National Nurses Organizing Committee, United American Nurses, and Massachusetts Nurses Association. Its purpose is to give registered nurses a national voice and organizing power. It is also affiliated with the AFL-CIO.
  - National Organization of Legal Services Workers (NOLSW), UAW Local 2320, Jan 2009-present
    The National Organization of Legal Services Workers (NOLSW), UAW Local 2320, represents the majority of those who work in federally-funded legal services programs across the United States. The local also represents workers in other types of law offices, various human services programs and other agencies.
  - National Postal Mail Handlers Union, Apr 2012-present
    The National Postal Mail Handlers Union, affiliated with the AFL-CIO and LIUNA, is the is the exclusive bargaining agent for 47,000 mail handlers who load, unload, prepare, sort, and containerize mail for the US Postal Service. The website contains news, multimedia, legislatives action alerts, and contract updates.
  - National Writers Union, Dec 2012-present
    The National Writers Union (NWU) represents freelance writers throughout the United States. It was formed in 1981 during the Writers' Congress held in New York City. In 1981, the NWU affiliated with the United Auto Workers (UAW) as Local 1981. As of 2011, the NWU has over 1,500 members in fifteen locals. The website contains news and chapter information.
  - New York Building Congress, Mar 2009-present
    The New York Building Congress, founded in 1921, is a coalition of 400 constituent organizations comprising more than 250,000 skilled trades people and professionals that works to advance economic and infrastructure investment and job creation. The Congress publishes reports and analysis related to building projects in New York City. The Congress also created the New York Building Foundation, which promotes research, education, and philanthropy in the construction industry.
  - New York Chapter of the National Writers Union, Local 1981, Feb 2009-present
    The National Writers Union, UAW Local 1981, is a labor union for freelance writers. The NWU advocates for writers' rights and fights to improve the income, contracts and working conditions for all freelance writers, including journalists, book authors, business and technical writers, essayists, poets, playwrights, script writers, writers for the web and campus writers. The NWU, founded in 1981, consists of 16 chapters throughout the country.
  - New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health, Feb 2007-present
    New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH), founded in 1980, is a non-profit coalition of 200 local unions and more than 400 individual workers, physicians, lawyers and other health and safety activists dedicated to the right of worker safety on the job. NYCOSH operates throughout New York City, Long Island and the Lower Hudson Valley. The website gives information and assistance for those injured on the job and other training and safety resources.
  - New York Hotel and Motel Trades Council, Mar 2009-present
    Founded in the 1930s, The New York Hotel and Motel Trades Council, AFL-CIO (Hotel Trades Council), is the union of hotel workers in New York City. The Council represents approximately 30,000 non-managerial employees working in all hotel departments, including: housekeeping, public space, dining room, banquet, room service, kitchen, stewarding, bar, mini-bar, audio-visual, front desk, reservations, PBX, bell and door services, concierge, night auditing, laundry, valet, engineering, maintenance, electrical, carpentry, painting, upholstery, business centers, night cleaning, health spas, security, garage, purchasing and receiving, and storeroom in over 300 hotels in the New York City area. It is affiliated with the SEIU, UNITE-HERE, OPEIU, IUOE, IBEW, IUPAT, and USWA.
  - New York Labor History Association, Apr 2009-present
    New York Labor History Association (NYLHA) was founded in 1976 by trade unionists, academics, students, archivists, educators, labor editors, attorneys, and retirees, mostly from New York State. NYLHA encourages the study of workers and their organizations and serves as a bridge between past and present labor unionists and academics.
  - New York State AFL-CIO, Sep 2007-present
    The New York State AFL-CIO, in 1958, is the federation of labor unions in New York State affiliated with the AFL-CIO (American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations).
  - New York State Public Employees Federation, Nov 2011-present
    Formed in 1978, New York State Public Employees Federation (PEF) is a local white-collar union, representing 55,599 professional, scientific, and technical public employees. PEF also represents employees who work in private-sector jobs and local government agencies including the Albany County Probation Department; Albany Housing Authority; NYS Canal Corporation; National Development and Research Inc; and, Lockport Memorial Hospital. The union publishes The Communicator, a newsletter with a 2007 distribution of 70,000, on a monthly basis
  - New York State United Teachers (NYSUT), Feb 2013-present
    New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) is a 600,000-member New York state teachers union, affiliated since 2006 with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), the AFL-CIO, and the National Education Association (NEA). NYSUT is a federation of over 1200 local unions in New York state; lobbies on the local, state and federal level; conducts research; and organizes new members. The website contains a blog, information in benefits, by-laws and contracts, and other resources.
  - New York Taxi Workers Alliance, May 2011-present
    New York Taxi Workers Alliance, founded in 1998, consists of 15,000 members of yellow taxicab drivers. NYTWA provides legal, health and financial services and improve working conditions through organizing, political and media advocacy, litigation, direct legal services, and access to healthcare. They are part of the Central Labor Council and the International Taxi Workers Alliance.
  - Newspaper Guild of New York, Local 3, Feb 2009-present
    The Newspaper Guild of New York, launched in 1934, is an labor union for people in the news and media business, including print, photo, video, and digital journalists, as well as employees in advertising, circulation and other related areas. They represent about 3,000 employees at New York area-based media organizations and their respective bureaus around the nation.
  - Office and Professional Employees International Union (OPEIU), Dec 2009-present
    Office and Professional Employees International Union is a trade union representing over 110,000 white-collar workers in the public and private sector, including workers in banking and credit unions, insurance, higher education, shipping, hospitals, medical clinics, utilities, transportation, hotels, and administrative offices. Professional organizations and Guilds affiliated with OPEIU are a diverse group that includes physicians, pharmacists, chiropractors, appraisers, podiatrists, clinical social workers, hypnotists, teachers, and helicopter pilots.
  - Operative Plasterers' and Cement Masons' International Association of the United States and Canada (OP&CMIA), Dec 2009-present
    The Operative Plasterers' and Cement Masons' International Association of the United States and Canada (OPCMIA), founded in 1864, is a trade union of plasterers and cement masons in the construction industry in the United States and Canada. Members of the union finish interior walls and ceilings of buildings and apply plaster on masonry, metal, and wire lath or gypsum. Cement masons are responsible for all concrete construction, including pouring and finishing of slabs, steps, wall tops, curbs and gutters, sidewalks, and paving. The organization is a member union of the AFL–CIO and Canadian Labour Congress.
  - Organization of Staff Analysts, Feb 2013-present
    Founded in 1970 by twelve employees of the New York City Department of Personnel as the Committee of Personnel Examiners, the Organization of Staff Analysts (OSA) became the official collective bargaining agent for Analysts in the Board of Education in 1985. OSA is a member of, and bargains collectively through, the Municipal Labor Committee. It represents employees of the City of New York in the Analyst title series serving in more than fifty city agencies. The website contains information on benefits, newsletter, and weekly newsline.
  - Organization United for Respect at Walmart (OUR Walmart), Nov 2012-present
    Organization United for Respect at Walmart (OUR Walmart), is an organization which works to make change in labor practices for Walmart associates, established in 2011. The organization works to change policy at Walmart, including the following changes: paying a minimum of $13/hour and make full-time jobs available for Associates who want them; creating dependable, predictable work schedules; providing affordable healthcare; providing every Associate with a policy manual; ensuring equal enforcement of policy and no discrimination; and giving every Associate equal opportunity to succeed and advance in his or her career. The group's website publishes associate stories and provides action alerts.
  - Professional Aviation Safety Specialists (PASS), Dec 2009-present
    The Professional Aviation Safety Specialists, AFL-CIO (PASS) represents approximately 11,000 Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) and Department of Defense (DoD) employees throughout the United States and in several foreign countries. PASS members include Technical Operations and DoD employees (systems specialists, electronics technicians and computer specialists), Flight Standards and manufacturing aviation safety inspectors, flight inspection pilots, missions specialists and procedures development specialists in Aviation System Standards, and administrative employees in the FAA’s Aviation Registry. In 1977, PASS was formed to provide representation for the FAA’s technician bargaining unit. PASS has grown over the decades and now represents five bargaining units within the FAA and DoD. PASS is dedicated to supporting and sustaining the safety and efficiency of the National Airspace System (NAS) for the flying public.
  - Professional Staff Congress/City University of New York, Sep 2007-present
    The Professional Staff Congress is the union that represents more than 20,000 faculty and staff at the City University of New York (CUNY). The union negotiates, administers and enforces collective bargaining agreements; protects the rights of staff through the grievance and arbitration process; engages in political activity on behalf of CUNY and its staff and students; and advocates for the interests of the instructional staff in various forums. It is affiliated with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), the American Association of University Professors (AAUP), the New York State United Teachers (NYSUT), and the NYC Central Labor Council (CLC).
  - Progressive Librarians Guild, Nov 2008-present
    The Progressive Librarians Guild, founded in 1990, is a forum for open exchange of radical views on library issues. The Guild conducts campaigns to support progressive and democratic library activities; supports activist librarians as they work to effect changes in their own libraries and communities; bridges the gaps between school, public, academic and special libraries, and between public and technical services; encourages debate about prevailing management strategies adopted directly from the business world and to propose democratic forms of library administration; considers the impact of technological change in the library workplace; monitors the professional ethics of librarianship from a perspective of social responsibility; and facilitates contacts between progressive librarians and other professional and scholarly groups in the record keeping field. The Guild publishes a journal, the Progressive Librarian.
  - Radicals at Work, Apr 2011-present
    Radicals at Work is a network of young activists and radicals involved in workers’ movements. The network works to build a stronger movement from the bottom-up. The website informs and educates on issues in the workers’ movement. The website has not been updated since mid-2010.
  - Remember the Triangle Fire Coalition, Sep 2012-present
    Remember the Triangle Fire Coalition, established for the centennial of the Triangle Shirtwaist factory fire, works to build of a public art memorial to honor the legacy of the Triangle factory workers and spread awareness of the fire through education and activism. The website contains information on the memorial design competition, an open archive of digitized material on the fire, labor activism in the early twentieth century, and the victims. The website also contains a names map, resources, and information about their centennial commemoration.
  - Restaurant Opportunities Centers United, Jul 2011-present
    Restaurant Opportunities Centers United (ROC-United), founded in 2001, is a national coalition of restaurant workers' organizations. It works to is to improve wages and working conditions for the nation’s low-wage restaurant workforce. ROC-United does extensive statistical research to understand the labor market in ROC-United regions.
  - Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union. Local 1-S Department Store Workers Union, Mar 2009-present
    Local 1-S is a local branch of the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union/UFCW (RWDSU), which represents Macy’s workers in the United States and 3,500 employees at the Macy’s department store in Herald Square, Manhattan. The union works to protect Macy's employees' right to the fair wages and benefits that allow them to support themselves and their families.
  - SAG-AFTRA, Feb 2012-present
    The website contains information on the merger in 2012 of the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) and American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA). It contains news related to the merger, events, frequently asked questions, and a page on merger materials.
  - Screen Actors Guild (SAG), Dec 2009-Sep 2012
    Screen Actors Guild (SAG), established in 1993, is an American labor union representing over 200,000 film and television performers worldwide. According to SAG's Mission Statement, the Guild seeks to: negotiate and enforce collective bargaining agreements that establish equitable levels of compensation, benefits, and working conditions for its performers; collect compensation for exploitation of recorded performances by its members, and provide protection against unauthorized use of those performances; and preserve and expand work opportunities for its members. SAG merged with AFTRA in March 2012.
  - Screen Actors Guild, New York Branch, Mar 2009-present
    The New York Branch of the Screen Actors Guild is one of twenty branches nationwide representing actors working in motion pictures, television, commercials, industrials, video games, Internet and all new media formats. The Guild exists to enhance actors working conditions, compensation and benefits and to be a powerful, unified voice on behalf of artists rights.
  - Seafarers International Union, Apr 2012-present
    Founded in 1938, The Seafarers International Union, Atlantic, Gulf, Lakes and Inland Waters District/NMU, AFL-CIO, represents unlicensed United States merchant mariners sailing aboard U.S.-flag vessels in the deep sea, Great Lakes and inland trades. The union also represents licensed U.S. mariners in the Great Lakes and inland sectors. The website contains information on their training center, the Paul Hall Center for Maritime Training and Education, news, and stories.
  - Service Employees International Union (SEIU), Dec 2009-present
    Service Employees International Union (SEIU), founded in 1921, is a labor union representing about 1.8 million workers in over 100 occupations in the United States (including Puerto Rico), and Canada. SEIU is focused on organizing workers in three sectors: health care (over half of members work in the health care field), including hospital, home care and nursing home workers; public services (local and state government employees); and, property services (including janitors, security officers and food service workers). It is affiliated with the Change to Win Federation and the Canadian Labour Congress.
  - Sheet Metal Workers International Association (SMWIA), Dec 2009-present
    The Sheet Metal Workers International Association, founded in 1888, is a trade union of skilled metal workers who perform architectural sheet metal work, fabricate and install heating and air conditioning work, shipbuilding, appliance construction, heater and boiler construction, precision and specialty parts manufacture, and a variety of other jobs involving sheet metal. The Sheet Metal Workers International Association represents about 150,000 members in 185 local unions in the United States and Canada.
  - Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local 137, Mar 2009-present
    The mission of the Sheet Metal Workers International Association, Local Union No. 137 is to organize, educate, and represent all workers in associated crafts in the New York region. The purpose of the Union is to represent all members in their fight to improve benefits, wages, and safe working conditions.
  - Social Service Employees Union Local 371, Sep 2007-present